Okay, Ajahn.
In the suttas, the knowledge of a
sotapanna is described in several
different ways.
I do find it hard to reconcile the one
about whatever is the nature to arise is
of the nature to cease, and he knows
kusala is kusala and akusala is akusala
and their root.
The first seems to be an understanding
of the nature of phenomena, whereas the
second one seems rather simple, \
\. Do these knowledges just different
Do these knowledges just different
phrasing, but do have the same meaning?
If so, what is their core message?
So, uh the
the knowledge of knowing
things in arising and ceasing,
basically, knowing that whatever has the
nature to arise has the nature to cease.
It's um
well, it even that can sound simplistic
in a sense that um
people can learn about impermanence.
And then um
once it makes sense, it feels like you
know it, and you know, you could ask
your average person, and they would say,
"Yeah, of course I know things are
subject to change. Everything is
changing. Everything is constantly
changing." But that's not the impermanence that the
But that's not the impermanence that the
Buddha was talking about, because if you
truly understand impermanence, you would
be free from suffering. You'll be
understanding the four noble truths. So,
when the insight of a sotapanna that um
whatever has the nature to arise has
nature to cease, that means like
on the most personal level,
he understands
unownability of things due to their
appearance. Not due to this, not due to that, not
Not due to this, not due to that, not
because electrons are constantly
changing, not because of somebody told
you, it's because
things have arisen
on their own.
So, the fact that you are subjected to
the appearance of things,
that appearance of things
shows you basically
um implies their impermanence.
So, doesn't matter your intention, doesn't
doesn't matter your intention, doesn't
matter your effort, doesn't matter
whether you ignore it or not. Once you
understand it on the level of appearance
means impermanence,
you can then take it from there rightly,
so to speak. That's why that's like the
beginning of the Noble Eightfold Path.
Uh and same goes with knowing um
skillful as skillful and unskillful as
unskillful. Exactly.
A person can anybody can learn about it
and then it can it can sort of
uh
make sense intellectually, reasonably.
And it's like, "Yeah, I know good things
are good, bad are bad. I know why good
why good is good, why bad is bad." But
all of that is like a secondary sort of
second-hand information that you would
have um
um
somewhat integrated. Let's put it that
way. But the reality is basically
But the reality is basically
um
a non sotapanna has no
internal reference point as to what
constitutes uh skillful skillful as skillful and
uh skillful skillful as skillful and
unskillful as unskillful. And that
internal reference point is your own
chitta. So, a non sotapanna does not see his own
So, a non sotapanna does not see his own
mind. Does not see his own wild animal.
Um so, uh the it will have I mean,
everybody will have their ideas and and
images in their mind when they think
about the mind.
Um
but that will not stand for that which
mind actually is.
That's why prerequisite for sotapatti's
uh seeing the the the signs and
characteristics of the mind,
chittanimitta. In other words, seeing
the mind as an actual living
entity which is neither in your sense sense
which is neither in your sense sense
objects nor in your senses. It's kind of
neither here nor there, yet it's real as
such. And you see it change its mood.
You see it has persists in certain
moods. Um so, that's why basically
Um so, that's why basically
a person who doesn't see their own mind
then then does not know what is actually
beneficial for that mind and what is
unbeneficial. So, a satipanna who who recognizes the
So, a satipanna who who recognizes the
characteristics of his own mind starts
seeing it, as I said, as a actual living
entity in the core of your being.
Um now he knows.
He can directly see has a has an
immediate simultaneous feedback as to
what is making this mind grow, calm
down, become more peaceful, and what is
making this wild animal more agitated,
uh more disturbed, more wild, less
obedient. In the same sense, you you trap, you
In the same sense, you you trap, you
know, you trap a wild dog or something,
as I often say,
and um
you have it in a fenced-off yard, and
when you let certain things come in its
visual range or audible range, it gets
very agitated.
Now, those things might not necessarily
be bad things in and of themselves.
Uh and
everybody might agree that those things
are actually good things.
And you could even reason that they're
good things, but all of those are
secondary criteria now. For you, the
most important the immediate criteria is
I don't care if the whole world says
doing this is good or doing that is bad.
My criteria is the recognition of what
does that make uh my mind do or want to
do.
And if you see that it's leading to
agitation, passion, increase of these
unwholesome things, it's unbeneficial.
It's akusala.
If you see that it's leading to calming,
um imperturbability,
dispassion above all, you know, oh, that
is kusala.
That is beneficial for taming of the
animal, which is for my welfare and the
welfare of the animal.
So, you could see that neither of those
insights are
I mean, they're not complex in terms of
you need to learn a lot of moving parts,
but they're nowhere near easily seen
because if they were, everybody would be a
if they were, everybody would be a
sotapanna.